uh I thought of talking about anapati
but not not like in terms of the
not not like in terms of the
technicalities of the
suta more like just individually but
what people
do when it comes to doing
it cuz obviously you know that Su like
all the other
suits it's uh due to its own kind of
form and the way it's preserved all you
get is these
outlines of the condensed statements
that mean a lot more than what's
expressed which is why obviously that
that whole suit been used to justify any
medit meditation technique or practice
you can come up
with because even the things that the
suta does describe they're not really
instructions of a specific nature
they're more like results
that you practice the
words so it says like breathing in you
gladdens the mind that's not something
you can just do immediately you read it
you immediately know what it is and you
immediately do it rightly it's
impossible knowingly breathing in
breathing out in the way the sud starts
again what what what is the knowledge of
the breath is it sensation in your
nostrils is that how you know you're
breathing so you realize every line
every um every step quote unquote it's
not really a step it's more like
something to work towards without
telling you in more detail how you work
towards it you have to infert that
yourself so putting
aside those steps in that
sense not regarding them as such but but
actually just if you think for yourself
okay what we do know it's say somebody
just as I said anybody comes the Su
impartially not arriving through the
meditation method or through this or
that but just reading what the Sut says
to the extent that it says
it it says that it leads to fulfillment
of the four foundations of
mindfulness that's
the culmination of anapanasati
so the mindness of the body the feeling
the mind and the images the
mind and the images the
Damas so we know that
much so how would you now in reference
to
that describe your practice
of non forgetfulness of
breathing and what would be the value of
it and what are the aspects of it
characteristics
things that are not clear things that
are clear I mean we talked about it
clear I mean we talked about it
differently in different talks and stuff
but forget about all
that let's try and be neutral
so how do you know if you're
breathing because you're breathing
that's cuz you Brea can see it do you
need to do you need
to do you need
to stop doing whatever you were
doing in order to find out that you were
breathing
well not in the sense of I need to stop
it in order to then you know do
something else and find out you're
breathing but you might kind of have to
stop it in to the extent that if
something is like completely you know
your mind is completely distracted and
you're completely absorbed in whatever
you're doing
mhm so you need to un absorb yourself un
absorb yourself a bit because you might
actually be kind of forgetting about
your breathing Yeah by doing lots of
other things on top of it but then so
does that mean you don't need to
concentrate in order to know that you're
breathing no I mean as then yes it does
mean that you does mean that so it means
that you need to UNC
concentrate from being too focused in
order to know that you're breathing so
why are then people practicing
concentration through the breathing
why is the entire terada practicing
concentration through the sensations of
the nostrils of the breathing because basically
because basically
um I would say like because the views
such as they are misguided or whatever
as you might say that they are
um are generally all kind of based on
this General notion that's taken for granted
General notion that's taken for granted
that um meditation in as much as any
other kind of task that you might
undertake to achieve
something um is something that you have
to be actively doing in order to get
certain result from it can you simplify
that people think that you have to be doing
people think that you have to be doing
the meditation mhm there you go it's
easier um so
yeah so that's the basic in initial yet
fundamental overlooking the knowledge of the breath
overlooking the knowledge of the breath
does not require your
concentration the knowledge does not
require concentration even in worldly
terms
so we ask how do you know you're
breathing because you're breathing what
else can be said about
that where did you find that where did
you find that
breath generally peripherally to what
what breath is you have to go into peripheral
breath is you have to go into peripheral
to see
it where where is
he where's the
breath the
body internal body body is
breathing can you breathe instead of the
body no impossible
but it's it's not necessarily clear
isn't
it like you can breathe but you not
doing the
breathing it always body has to do it
it's always bound with the body
Inseparable from so how you do how you or rather
from so how you do how you or rather
what is your role in it is there a room
for you
there no if you if you see that it's the
body breathing then there
isn't then there isn't yeah
but the other aspect now that can be
uncovered well that can be covered up by
saying okay so it's the body always
breathing does that mean you have no say
in it exactly no it's the opposite it's
like because there are things that you
just sort of uh can
feel like the heartbeat for example that
is the body the heart is doing it and
that you truly have no saying like you
can yeah doesn't doesn't make any
difference what you think or what you
intend but the breath is always
intentional yeah so it's your
intention for body to
breathe so why is that important why
can't you just say it's my intention to
breathe or just the body's
breathing why do you need to include
both because that's kind of where the
there's a there's a a blurring of
boundaries there let say as in the that
your intention kind of goes into the
body and makes it breathe yeah in the
same way as like with yeah ex and
whenever there is bluring of the
boundaries between the Aggregates there
is ownership there is
conceiving there is daa
so that's how you would be developing
the Sati patana of the
body to its
fulfillment e to not bluring the
boundaries of the extent of the bodily
breath but it does not mean overlooking
the intentional
aspect of it that does not pertain to
the body that's not
bodily so any it's not making the
body some do something you know like
make it do something or become something
other than what it is it's kind to
revealing what is the body well it's
revealing what's already
Inseparable and in temperable activity
of the
body so and again that the same
principle of
you having an intentional input in the
breathing but not being able to not make
it bodily or make it yours it's your
whole relationship with the entire body
moving your arms legs head eating
sleeping it's exactly it shares the same
nature you are doing those things cuz
the body can do those things
M but you don't see that separation so
to speak so you are very much gried with
the desire and ownership of doing or
avoiding those things while they truly
always remained on the domain of the
body and
physical so what else then actually
before we started this we should have
said
if you were to um well if you were to
practice mindfulness of
breathing what expectations do you
have what do you expect to come out of
out of
that yeah it's
probably what do I talk talk
but do you have any expectations if you
sit down say okay I'll sit down now I
finish all the work hold the duties
things are
quiet mind is relatively free from
hindrances as far as I can see
it let me practice on a panas
Sati do you have implicit
expectations for something to come out
of that
practice or you doing it for its own
sake that's actually something something
was thinking
about kind of in relation to that
subject as well
like yeah anapanasati in particular or
any you know specific let me sit down
and do this thing it feels like it
almost must carry some expectation M
with it um and that and then you kind of
it um and that and then you kind of
catch your mind say okay having sort of
an expectation from it
and um and I would catch that and kind
of with draw from
it and then the other kind of thing that
would come with that is like well but
then what's the point of doing it you
know it feels like it should you know
well it's kind of this artificial thing
but so is this is that expectation would
you have such expectations if you doing
Sati
panas if you're mindful of your body
postures would you have same
expectations as if you were doing
ananti no why is that CU it's the same
practice exactly exactly that was and
that was what I then thought that it's
like actually it's um it's you who make
it into something that you know is a is
a
specific practice that carries
expectations or yeah I think it's
probably because you know how we all
arrived it this from one angle or the
other with the ideas of well
misconceived ideas of meditation being
state of
heighten Consciousness through your
concentration releases and Novelty
experiences and self hypnotic
transes so anapanasati was always
mentioned in those you know and you have
all those other Yogi practices of breath
and visualizations and tantas and
energies and so on so it's kind of hard
to just sit down and breathe without the
implicit yeah but also when is it what
is it what what should happen here
now but as I said according to the sutas
it's the practice of satana it's the
practice of for that brings the for
foundations of mindfulness to
fulfillment that's
it so why don't you then have the same
ecstatic expectations
about sitting standing walking lying
down feeling Pleasant unpleasant neutral
seeing mind is elevated depressed
expanded shrunk light
heavy thinking impermanence for Noble
Truths but it's you wouldn't yeah but
you should or then you should evaluate your
should or then you should evaluate your
expectations of
anapati so it outlines the domain of the
body mindfulness of the breath not
forgetfulness of the breath so how else
what else can be said in your own words
in terms of how do you practice non
forgetfulness of the breathing
how would you do it for example to come
and ask you okay don't tell me any
contemporary meditation technique
nothing like that just tell
me how do I develop non forgetfulness of
my own breath
what would you describe to
me so there's the
perception there's that direction but
there's also I don't know what that
means okay I don't understand any of
that I just want to know how do I not
forget about my
breathing your grandmother is asking you
that's it what do I do son tell you're going
it what do I do son tell you're going
about your day I go by my day and while
you're going by what would you recommend
to me then are you breathing while you
go are you breathing right now but I
forget I keep forgetting it how do I not
forget it
to can I carry on about my
day the way as before yeah really
well it's depends on it depends on what
am I doing throughout the day exactly
right so you would want to say okay
so if your actions are too
distracting you do need to well reduce
the amount of your involvement with them
because you cannot possibly it's not
about attending to your breath you know
you don't need to attend to it to know
that you're breathing but you certainly
cannot be attending to something else
fully immersed in it as you just said
and expect to not so a degree of that
peripheral recognition that you are
breathing here and now this body is
doing the breathing needs to be allowed
for the space for that needs to be
allowed for so then the tasks that
you're doing can't
be requiring too much of your attention
now that depends on the person how much
is too
much you know like a blanket
formula but say okay I still find that
even hard I minimize the tasks can can I
just sit down
maybe and then do that non forgetfulness
of breathing should I sit down and try
and do it do it in
that more stilled manner or should I
just not sit down and
continue moving about and trying not to
forget about my
breathing it's it's not it's not a trick
question yeah I mean you you should you
should you should that's that's what the
instruction says
itself because yeah you will be
forgetting about breathing that's kind
of the
point and then including that and then
not when you forget about breathing and
then when you in when you're aware that
you forgot about your breathing you
don't then run back fully attending to
the sensations of your breath in order
to remember it because it's
unnecessary you just need to remember
that you forgot about it and when you do
you see the breathing
there so knowingly you breathe in
knowingly you breathe out the degree of
that knowledge can change it does not
need to always be in front of your
mind that's the point and that's the
practice so basically it's the training
in
y it's training in seeing the origin or
true to the origin or the source or the
boom of whatever is in front of you
being attended where your attention
rests so the breathing becomes a
reference point for
that and it's particularly well I
shouldn't say so why is it particularly
useful cuz it's
neutral there's a battery warning or
something well it's neutral yes but
why could you just carry on watching
your for body
postures CU there's intention involve
it's intention involved exactly yeah so
it it it does highlight that whole
aspect of intentional
involvement which can then hopefully as
we said in the beginning
clarify outline the extent of the physicality
outline the extent of the physicality
because Often by overlooking your
intentions you kind of place yourself in
that body take the ownership of that
breath because yes there you you do have
control degree of control over it but
that still does not take it out of the
physical domain into the domain of your
intention and your ownership not at all
and it's hammering in
that kind of basic
recognition so what else can come out of
mindfulness of
breath the four Great elements would be
one example of
when you saying about
how the uh these yeah the the overlap
doesn't doesn't exist so it's
like yeah the four the four Great
elements that are completely outside of
my
control uh yeah so then the
nature of your
of your
control being completely secondary to
the things you're
controlling your sense of control being
completely enclosed within
that again that's something people can
understand and intellectually and wrap
their head around but there are layers
to that and there levels that that thing
needs to sink in
so what else so you don't have mystical
ecstatic expectations of youran
panas you're just knowing the breathing
through practicing non forgetfulness of
it in a controlled environment not in
the middle of a
busy bus stop or something although you
could if you're doing it rightly
what else what else would be the benefit
of
that what else would be the benefit of
practicing the discernment of your
intentional involvement with a physical
breath without taking it up with
yours well the mind becoming kind of
withdrawn from the animal calming down I was yeah
from the animal calming down I was yeah
was I mean that was going to say
initially but then the way you asked
made it sound more so I was just going
to say the Mind becomes
c um
um
because but would the Mind always become
C could you become depressed as a
result I wouldn't sayug
slow tired well s there might be that
but not as a result of doing it
rightly but I guess those things would
come up that's ex that's one thing you
are doing it rightly but the mind is
still the Mind
MH that's why it's not like you only
observe the happy elated mind in the
practice of saatana of the mind no you
see it as depressed which means he might
well be depressed cuz he doesn't want to
be sitting and recollecting the reading
now especially when you took the the the
trans exatic astr projection element out
of
it yeah you're not because you're
depressed doesn't mean you're doing it
wrong exactly exactly good
exactly exactly good
news no that that is the point the point
is the drilling the point is the
training the point is the
work the training he he trains himself D
he's doing it regardless of how he feels
and regardless of what his wrong views
might still be expecting to come out of
it but it doesn't mean he's doing it
mechanically either because how can you
mechanically be intending to not forget
about intentional aspect of your
breathing that belongs to the
body good
luck you
can if you start doing it mechanically
it won't be on the level of the
knowledge of the breath you know that
the body is breathing
you don't need to concentrate on your
nostril to find it out you don't need to
feel the movements in your belly you
know the breath is there in as much you
know you're seated or standing or
walking or lying down exactly the
same but yes it would
come well it would come the um
intentional involvement with the mental
activity with the activity of the mind
of the Mind mind still might be
elated or depressed but your intentional
involvement on account of the mood that
that mind is in well that will
lessen that will be that will
subside cuz the you know it's the mind
that presents you that wants you to
think about this or that and pressures
you towards it but it's you giving into
it and then self fueling the the the
the Vicious Cycles of of just
revolving out of things that make you
angry because of which you revolve
around them because of which they make
you more angry and so on or lustful but
if you were to refer back to the SAT
patan of the body through the knowledge
of it not through the misconceived
observation of your
Sensations through the knowledge of it
you are moving your intentional
involvement elsewhere so that the Mind still might
elsewhere so that the Mind still might
be pressuring you now you can see ah
there is the experience of the
pressuring
mind so you create space between the two
between you and the
M that's why it does
sound suas and it's actually even
compared like the wheel turner wasn't it
was the wheel turner I was going to
mention that simil as well yeah yeah it
sounds like uh okay no I'm going to do
this task now so I shall go and I shall
be planning some
wood I don't have time now to indulge
the whims of my mind that wants me to
think about this or that maybe I'll do
it later maybe I won't now I'm just
going to sit and do this task and to the
extent I do it to that extent I'll know
I'm doing
it so it kind of provides an indirect
reference for whatever you're being
pressured by so you're not doing it to get rid of
by so you're not doing it to get rid of
the
mind you're not doing it to get a
mystical experience as a result of it
you're doing it simply to hammer it in
the fact that the body comes
first the bodily activity comes first
the bodily domain comes first and you're
fully enclosed within
it there is no outside of
that despite what your mind tries to
make you
believe how would you say that's another
way of
um or another benefit or another way of
expressing the benefit is that it's revealing
it's revealing
um a level of well yeah activity
activity
that's that you're doing that's going on
but and that's um
um
not requiring any passion basically not
requiring any and that's and that never
is like you're and it's always you
realize it's below your passion it's
below the threshold it's below your
passionate threshold of your passionate
Pro will and as much as then like you can
will and as much as then like you can
say well like whether you want it or not
like the eyes are always seeing things
the ears are always hearing hear level
and just there but then there's this and
then you kind of go this extra step of
like seeking out particular things but
you can kind of so the thing is learn to
operate the passion is real the
experience of passion is real the
experience of ill will is
real it's not about denying it MH and
it's not even about well you won't be
able to prevent it to make it just tell
it to stop coming you can't because
they're the result of a mind that's not
awakened that's that that's still not
free from ignorance which means whether
you wish or not to stop the passion or
real will it makes no difference it
won't stop so you can only undermine
stop so you can only undermine
it so you undermine it as we said many
times by not acting out of it by
containing it by purify your mind
purifying your mind in De but in this
particular context of this practice of
saan in general and anati well you
undermine it see there is a a passion
mind of passion and there is pressuring
thoughts passionate thoughts that mind
wants you to
think now I can be focusing my breath
and really narrowing down concentration
so I stopped thinking about this mind
it's like no you're just acting out of a
verion you're trying to get rid of it
you're trying to make you go away
because it bothers me so much you are
not certainly uprooting it and let alone
understanding it no you don't want to
get rid of it you want to contain
it when I talk about enduring things on
the right
level that's why I refer to it as like
patience because patience contains
things so you already contain it through
not acting out but now you can contain
it even more so you say you have a mind
of passion pressuring thoughts of
passion or ill will or whatever
hindrance within
that there is a knowledge of breathing
on that physical
domain it doesn't matter how big that
passion or anger gets how strong that
pressure increases it can
never come over the underlying physical
domain can never spill outside
and even if you act out of
it it's actually not spilling outside
it's your own
ignorance perturbing the the order of
the picture but fundamentally the
physical domain the domain of the senses
the domain of the knowledge of that
breath Inseparable from the body it's
always underneath the threshold of your
intentional involvement with passion ill
will distraction and so on
so by Discerning that by cultivating
that by training yourself in it you are
training yourself in the right
order even if you don't think about the
right order or not you are putting your
passion second you're not trying to get
rid of it
blindly through ill will through denial
through more craving against it you're
containing it exactly how you would
contain the fire until it runs out of
oxygen and it will run out of oxygen
CU oxygen comes from outside but when
there is no outside to
this it cannot
persist and yeah exactly you got rid of
it just in the right
way without you needing to Crave against
it so that's you know I was saying that
in other talks long time ago you know
you can have your mind
preoccupied with stuff IDE and so on but
you can always discern peripherally that
you just in the midst of that like
deeply engaging passionate
engaging passionate
involvement of your mental level you
find your body just there scratching
oozing sitting breathing this this thing
this creature oblivious to all your worries
creature oblivious to all your worries
and projects and whatever else is just
just there and then you Overlook it then
you ignore it and then you continue to
prioritize your intentional level of
your engagements of your spilling out of
your acting
out and why is that possible because you
haven't trained yourself sufficiently
enough in the right order but if you do
then even if you don't wish and
want for the body to contain the
passionate project it will because
that's the Order of Things
even if you don't wish oh you
know may I stop regarding this this mind
this mind stop identifying with it stop
suffering and being pressur on account
of it well you will stop because you're
containing it and you're removing the
fuel for its Wilderness for its passion
that fuel being nothing other than that
wrong order that was the source of it it
overstepping misconceiving
so the practice of mindfulness of
breathing the practice of non
forgetfulness of the breath is the
practice of
Yara not directly attending to your
breathing but Discerning that you
already know you're breathing even if
you don't attend to
it that's the key
and what would you do if you get too
involved with your
breath is that a [Music]
problem do the same thing which one you
would be outlining that
involvement you would again you would
out have you outline your
body no no but what I mean if if you get
too involved with your breath say you
are recollecting the knowledge of
breathing correctly but now you're
feeling your lungs and energies and just
just overly attending to well you have
to basically
just do the same like what you just said
in regard to any passionate intention or
any we might not be passionate but say
you are overly focused on your breathing
yeah yeah is that a problem yes it is a problem the
problem the
feeling not but the breathing the point
is you don't have to stop breathing in
order to resolve the problem okay
because the problem is not that like
you're breathing too much the problem is
that you are like becoming uh overly
involved as you said by either like I
will try and do it like this I will try
and focus it on like that but you see
you can discern there's a difference
because you don't need to to do all of
that in order to breathe yeah so you
already breathing like normally before you then
breathing like normally before you then
start yeah so we covered all that so if
you do but you do find yourself too
focus and so how do you stop that the
feeling is the counterpart to that
becoming too absorbed that there is a
um the to
to to see
that pressure then then I would say
feeling becomes more relevant in as a
way to just keep it within the same just
just breathing that's not complicated I
mean it might work what you're saying
but so you're knowing your breathing the
next thing you know you're just
feeling the breath too much that's all
you think
about you're focused on it
just remember remember what the breath
exactly exactly so you you are you you
stop over doing it in the same sense you
stop underdoing it like despite your how
How Deeply involved you might become
with it and absorbed and like losing the
perception of everything else it's like
oh hold but I forgot that I know that
I'm already breathing that the body is
already
breathing so you remember the
breathing I like this I you saying
almost a whole B
water so yeah you remember you remember
that you already know you're
breathing and that un focuses you cuz
focusing means losing
perspective focusing means
yeah however you spin it the blurring of
the boundaries like the boundaries all
blurred exact just gone but that
unfocusing and like I just say you
mentioned outlining confining you know
unblurring those
boundaries and it's like that's
an that's sense space contemplation
sense objects sense Consciousness sense
cont feeling so it's like all that is
the same thing as under pan just
outlining things and undermining you
know outlining outlining the domains
undermining theing by clarifying it
which is yourself the blurs so
blurs so
um how should then one
understand the following instructions in
when you are supposed to breathe in long
and short
developing does doesn't that mean that
you need to be more involved with the
breath more focused on
it no not more involved not more F
certainly not more
focused
um well basically first like if you were
able to see clearly enough
to see clearly enough
the intentionality of it mhm you can
then sort of start exercising it
further yeah so to speak without losing
perspective cuz that's the point yeah
you don't start
immediately by overly intentionally
involving yourself with the breath
because you're already well the the
boundaries are already blurred you need
to start through knowledge knowledge of
the breathing it outlines the knowledge
of your intention to breathe
that's what I meant like those are not
steps that and you just do right off the
bat I read it and I do it first thing I
think of when I read that Su that's what
that Su means yeah good luck with that
really and that can be said for any Su
actually so it's like no you those are
the aspects that you would have worked
towards so if if you outlined
intentionality of your breathing
sufficiently enough the physicality of
your body
that is the
container of anything any subsequent
mind state or intention or whatever is
second to it within it then yes it can
push that intentionality further without
bluring the boundaries that's the
point cuz he still knowingly breathes in
long and knowingly breathes out long
knowingly while breathing
in feels the body
discerns the
mind contemplates
impermanence but why why can't you just
feel the body discern the Mind contempla
permanence
directly or you can but why is this
recommended
way because uh the permanence in the
body that you'll be recollecting is your
own idea yeah that's the risk of it yeah
but that is
rooted in the same basically well the
cause of that would be the reason why
you should be doing anati so still
doesn't ask my question as to why you
should be contemplating those things
through Sati panas as opposed to just do
it yourself well okay
so I think it's about basically
balancing like what you said in the
beginning this you can kind of go too
far in the direction of oh it's just the
body doing it and now I'm just like
observing it kind of from the outside
almost and you can go too far in the
direction of like I'm going to be fully
the one doing
it controlling everything and of
it
so so it's about
basically not doing too much of either
not going too much in either direction
but so if you just kind of stay only on
the level of knowledge of the breath
which you is valid and can already take
you quite far yeah there's a risk or the
there is a risk of the intentionality
aspect of it not become not being clear
enough I would say like it's just going
to be kind of a recollection of
something that you're not doing
deliberately or it's not like it's it's
a kind of oh yeah sure I know about it
but it's not I don't think that's what
I'm asking though okay so what are you
asking so what I'm asking is you can
directly contemplate impermanence okay
this you can directly contemplate your
mind or you can do it through
anti or saatana and given the way the
Buddha was talking about it seems to
indicate that it's better to do
itana why what's the
difference because it makes those
contemplations concrete well that's evident enough
concrete well that's evident enough
that's why it's better but that still
doesn't explain the
difference why are these concrete and
these are not so
concrete what's the
factor that determines the concreteness
of your contemplation movement
contemplation movement
no what's the single factor that follows
through we already said it like three or
four times now because
it through has to be done through
because of because
of because
of full stop because can become
something you take for
granted you familiar with it you are
developed in it to some
extent and yes when you attend to things
directly in other words you are
attending those things through
y to some
extent but not fully cuz if you were
well you would be an
ourand so then although you already know
the principle of yasara inside out you
haven't fully trained in it
yourself how do you know cuz you're not
an arant
yet so that's exactly why basati was
instructed toak Anam those who still had some work
toak Anam those who still had some work
to do
that's exactly why they could understand
it because okay yeah of course I I
absolutely have mastered the knowledge
of Yara inside out I can explain it in
hundreds of ways but am I an hunt yet no
means that Yara has not been thoroughly
developed I haven't trained in it
sufficiently enough and that's exactly
what you would do through satti whether
you want it or
not because it will prevent
you or it will
maintain a a degree of that a necessary degree of
a a degree of that a necessary degree of
that indirectness
indirectness to your contemplation of
impermanence through your cont through
your Discerning and communicating with
your chitt and and so
on that you can
Overlook or neglect
so yeah so it anchors it
essentially so through recollect not
forgetfulness of the knowledge of your
body breathing Here and
Now everything that's there with
there with
it you regard as
impermanent and the tendency
to if you were to have
it to but let me now go into those
things and really see them as
impermanent that's what we
doing that's taking away from
your so instead of giving into that
tendency to go and overdo it you stay
anchored you stay with the right
reference point peripheral knowledge of
the body
breathing and just allow
the perception of impermanence in regard
to those things to that extent that they
are revealed you don't need to reveal
them more and train in
that same in regard to the feelings
in regard to the state of the
animal the it's like this I don't need to fix
the it's like this I don't need to fix
it I don't need to change it well now
it's like this again I don't need to fix
it I don't need to change it I don't
need to do anything on account of
it and that becomes clearer and clearer
if you remain
anchored if you remain seeing it indirectly for